Guide to the Joseph Head Marshall Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Joseph Head Marshall papers
1800-1836
GEN MSS 1120
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.09
(5 boxes)
Correspondence, notes, writings, records of payments, espionage reports, a diary, and a code book, dating from 1800 to 1836, documenting Marshall's career as a double and sometimes triple agent during the Napoleonic period and the Bourbon Restoration. The material is bound in 26 volumes numbered 1-22 and 24-27, with most volumes containing a manuscript list of contents presumably prepared by a former owner.
Marshall, Joseph Head
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Hans P. Kraus, 1967.
Biographical/Historical note
Joseph Head Marshall was a medical doctor who was a master spy during the Napoleonic era, working for the English and the Bourbon kings of France.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, notes, writings, records of payments, espionage reports, a diary, and a code book, dating from 1800 to 1836, documenting Marshall's career as a double and sometimes triple agent during the Napoleonic period and the Bourbon Restoration. The material is bound in 26 volumes numbered 1-22 and 23-27, with most volumes containing a manuscript list of contents presumably prepared by a former owner.
Arrangement
Arranged by volume number.
Espionage, British -- France; Napoleonic Wars, 1800-1815; Spies -- France; Spies -- Great Britain; France -- Foreign relations -- 19th century; France -- History -- Restoration, 1814-1830; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- 19th century; Spies -- France -- 19th century; Spies -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Marshall, Joseph Head
- Volume 1, 1800-1825 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence to Marshall at various addresses in London and France, and letters of introduction.
- Volume 2, 1814-1816 (Box 1)
  Records of payments, most in French, signed by Marshall and countersigned by various individuals.
- Volume 3, 1815-1816 (Box 1)
  Correspondence, signed and unsigned, to Marshall with no address leaf.
- Volume 4, 1815-1836 (Box 1)
  Correspondence from multiple correspondents, signed and unsigned, to Marshall at various addresses in England and France, and without address leaf.
- Volume 5, 1816 February-1817 August (Box 1)
  Reports without salutations or signatures written in English to Marshall at Rue Pigalle, Paris, and stamped "ANGLETERRE" on address leaf.
- Volume 6, 1816 July-1816 December (Box 1)
- Volume 7, 1816-1822 (Box 1)
  Notes and writings in French and English, and extracts of letters.
- Volume 8, 1815-1825 (Box 2)
  Correspondence, including invitations from the Duke of Wellington to Marshall on Manchester Street, London, and the Rue Pigalle, Paris.
- Volume 9, 1817 (Box 2)
  Correspondence/reports without salutations or signatures written in English to Marshall at Rue Pigalle, Paris, and stamped "ANGLETERRE" on address leaf.
- Volume 10, 1817-1825 (Box 2)
  "Remarques sur une journée dans le Sud de la France," in French with English translation; with correspondence and a list of French and English names and addresses in Paris.
- Volume 11, 1817 (Box 2)
- Volume 12, 1817 (Box 2)
  Correspondence/reports without salutations or signatures and no address leaf to Marshall in London and Paris.
- Volume 13, 1818 July-December (Box 2)
  Correspondence/reports without salutations or signatures, sent from London to Marshall on Rue Pigalle, Paris.
- Volume 14, 1818 January-May (Box 3)
- Volume 15, 1819 February-December (Box 3)
- Volume 16, 1820 January-June (Box 3)
- Volume 17, 1820 July-December (Box 3)
  Correspondence/reports without salutations or signatures, sent from London to Marshall in Paris, with no street address on address leaf.
- Volume 18, 1821 January-June (Box 4)
- Volume 19, 1815, 1821 July-December, 1824 (Box 4)
- Volume 20, 1822 January-November (Box 4)
- Volume 21, 1823 January-December (Box 4)
- Volume 22, 1824 January-August (Box 4)
  Correspondence/reports, signed and unsigned, addressed to Marshall at No. 22 Manchester Street, Manchester Square, and other addresses in London and Paris.
- Volume 24, 1824-1825 (Box 5)
  Diary containing entries regarding meetings with politicians, royals, and others, and transcriptions of various documents.
- Volume 25, 1825 (Box 5)
  Correspondence/reports, signed and unsigned, addressed to Marshall in Portman Square and Temple Palace, Blackfriars Road, London; with "Song June Nancy Dawson," lyrics in eight stanzas.
- Volume 26, 1825 January-1826 January (Box 5)
  Correspondence/reports, signed "B" from Paris, to Marshall with no address leaf.
- Volume 27, undated (Box 5)
  Code book.